potassium has a host of cardiovascular
benefits and we've discussed some of
that clinical data in the past however
what no one has ever discussed is
exactly how pottassium has these heart
protecting effects well I mean it's not
common knowledge and I'd like to change
that there's one pretty influential
paper that combines biophysics and
bioengineering with physiology as
researchers used a colloidal Atomic
Force microscope which I'm sure you just
like me have one of those in your living
room to identify the impact that
potassium has on endothelial cells
endothelial cells if you were to zoom
into your blood vessels are the lining
of the cells that face the bloodstream
they control blood pressure by releasing
a variety of molecules that bind a
deeper layer of the cells called the
smooth muscle cells these muscle cells
are responsible for shrinking or opening
the blood vessels if they shrink it they
increase blood pressure and if they
relax it they reduce blood pressure and
since high blood pressure is intimately
tied to cardiovascular disease it's
reasonable to look at these cells and
know how potassium might affect them
they discovered that pottassium
softens endothelial cells so what does
that mean I mean did they use dowy
fabric softener well not quite in fact
not at all looking at the data we see
endothelial cell stiffness on the
vertical axis the higher the number the
greater the stiffness and then there's
four different conditions the cells are
exposed to different levels of sodium
and the addition of a blood pressure
hormone aldosterone now generally when
aldosterone binds to endothelial cells
it promotes the activation of the sodium
channels which allow sodium into the
cell increasing water retention and cell
stiffness however as we see with
increasing potassium levels added to the
cells indicated on the horizontal axis
cell stiffness was reduced I.E softening
the cells which might contribute to
combating cardiovascular disease like
arteriosclerosis so how does potassium
do that well the researchers believe
that potassium changes the formation of
a protein inside the
cells we're about to get a layer deeper
so buckle in your cells contain proteins
called actin proteins these proteins are
made into single units so called G actin
but the cell pulls them together into a
filamentous version meaning a linear
version of many single units bound
together called eth actin this protein
in its eatin form supports the structure
of the cell think of it like the
skeleton for the cell if more F actin is
around the cell tends to be more rigid
so stiff potassium seems to change fa
actin into G actin depolymerizing the
Fatin and it turns out that g actin
colocalizes it is found nearby a key
protein called nitric oxide synthese
which produces an important blood
pressure reducing molecule called nitric
oxide so nitric oxide is one of those
molecules that gets released by the
endothelial cells and binds smooth
muscle cells forcing them to relax and
therefore relax the blood vessel so
gacon somehow in influences possibly by
interaction nitric oxide synthese to be
more active producing more nitric oxide
in fact we see that evidence at least in
part here again we have sodium
conditions and we have elderone
conditions the vertical axis is a
measure of nitrite so a breakdown
product of nitric oxide and the
horizontal axis is a stepwise increase
in potassium administer to the
endothelial cells of note the higher the
nitrite the assumption is that Nitric ox
oide levels are greater I would have
liked to actually have seen some direct
measure of nitric oxide or some
confirmation measurement because it's
this measure just can get pretty muddied
but we can clearly see that when sodium
is low and the blood pressure promoting
aldosterone is not present nitrite
levels are elevated and more so when
pottassium is at a greater concentration
so this suggests that indeed potassium
raises nitric oxide levels however this
doesn't tell us the exact mechanism also
before we go on to another fascinating
mechanism I should point out that the
researchers used the wrong statistics
throughout their paper for those in the
statistics field they used an unpaired
student T test for multiple comparisons
actually multiple repeated comparisons
for the majority of you I don't think
this changes the results because the
effects are just so dramatic but I
should point out because well we can't
take studies at face value
now turning to a narrative review on the
matter where in the researchers point
out that potassium increases the
diameter of the blood vessel by relaxing
smooth muscle cells remember those are
the ones that directly relax or tighten
the blood vessel the smooth muscle cells
become hyperpolarized which means that
there are a more negative inside the
cell than the exterior of the cell which
shuts down their activation to contract
and therefore the blood vessel relaxes
increases the diameter of the blood
vessel and reducing blood pressure
that's all made possible because
potassium is a positive ion and it can
accumulate in the extracellular space
creating a more positive environment
around the cell than the inside of the
cell that's that hyperpolarization that
we just went over now in relation to
this there's something really cool that
exercise does that involves potassium
too oh also there's some work on
hyperpolar polarization factors these
molecules and the direct relationship
between smooth muscle cells and
endothelial cells I'll be covering that
in the extended version of this video
that you're watching part of the
physionic Insiders it's linked in the
description if you're interested in the
my premium research review delivered to
you weekly now as for the exercise the
researchers point out that when we
undergo skeletal muscle contraction
those are the muscle cells in your legs
in your arms and so on not to be
confused with the smooth muscle cells
that we've been discussing the muscle
contractions themselves kick potassium
out of the cells into the tiny arterials
in doing so this raises the
extracellular pottassium but the coolest
part is that once potassium is greater
in the extracellular space it can also
stimulate the sodium potassium pump to
activate there's this uh pump that kicks
out three sodium ions and adds two
pottassium ions into the cell since
potassium and sodium are both positive
ions but you're kicking out three sodium
per two potassium that makes a net
reduction in the positivity of the cell
making it more negative again if this is
happening to smooth muscle cells it's
making the blood vessel open up so in
the end we've been focused solely on the
mechanisms which make an incomplete
education on potassium's blood pressure
effects but we do know potassium reduces
blood pressure so the takeaway here is
that to make sure to keep your eye on
your potassium intake and to go over the
clinical data and go over the potassium
sources as well as cover one more major
mechanism while then check out this
upcoming video thanks for hanging out
[Music]